Guide to the James Hazen Hyde Papers 1874-1940, 1953 MS 319
New-York Historical Society
- Series III. Correspondence Concerning Federation de l'Alliance Francaise, 1898-1935 (bulk 1902-1908, 1922-1933); 1.67 Linear feet in 4 boxes
  In 1902, Hyde perceived that there were various groups throughout the United States and Canada active in extending the knowledge of French language, literature and art in those countries. He consequently founded an organization linking all these societies together: the Federation of French Alliances in the United States and Canada (Federation de l'Alliance Francaise aux Etats-Unis et au Canada). Among the Franco-American societies affiliated with the Federation, and represented in this collection, was the l'Alliance Francaise de New York. A principal activity of the central organization was bringing French lecturers to tour the countries. Hyde became the first president of the Federation and the secretariat was located in the offices of the Equitable. In 1903, Hyde was succeeded in the presidency by Julian Leroy White of the Alliance Francaise of Baltimore. In subsequent years, with Hyde's departure from the Equitable and the United States, especially after about 1908, he was no longer involved with the Alliance or Federation, though he continued to be involved with cultural exchanges in France. In the early 1920s, new leadership of the Federation, notably President Frank D. Pavey, reached out to Hyde for financial assistance, eventually leading to Hyde's renewed engagement with the organization from 1922 forward.
  The series includes correspondence concerning the Federation de l'Alliance Francaise aux Etats-Unis et au Canada and related organizations in France and the United States. The correspondence divides between two periods, from about 1900 to about 1915 and from 1921 to 1935. The gap relates to Hyde's relative lack of involvement in the Federation at that time.
  For the earlier period, Hyde's correspondence is principally with the officers of the Federation, its affiliated chapters in various cities of the United States, and officers of the sponsoring Alliance in Paris. Much of this earlier correspondence is directed to or from L.V. Gofflot, the Secretary General of the Federation. Among the many correspondents are Felix Weill, J. LeRoy White, L. Fiedler, Henry Cachard, W.H. Perkins, Rene Millet, Camille Thurwanger, A. Bousquet, Maxime Ingres, Henry L. Rippe, F. C. de Sumichrast, Anatole Le Braz, Julien Tiersot, Vicomte G. d'Avenel, Robert Lebaudy, Alcee Fortier, M. Jusserand, George Lamouret, E.H. Goulesque, Frank L. Warren Jr., Camille Gorde, and Henry Bargy. In the later period, the bulk of the correspondence is with the Federation's President Frank Pavey and Secretary General Felix Weill.
  The contents are primarily in French, though the later correspondence from Pavey is most commonly in English. The subject matter often concerns plans for lecturers from France to tour America, but administrative, governance, and financial matters are also discussed. The correspondence of 1922 includes reference to the reasons for Hyde reducing his activity in the Federation and his interest in re-engaging at that time.
  The documents have largely been left as found by the processing archivist, with some changes. The material was largely ordered in reverse chronological sequence; this remains the case in most instances, though some documents wee re-arranged to a straight chronological order to facilitate use. Many folders originally had what seemed to be several documents of outlying dates; these were smoothed in most cases to focus folders on more narrow time periods. Also, many documents were fastened with pins, but these were removed.
  - Correspondence. Alliance Francaise de Paris (4 folders), 1898-1908 (Box 15, Folder 1-4)
    Correspondence to Hyde from the Secretary General and others of the Alliance in Paris.
  - Correspondence. Federation de l'Alliance (4 folders), 1900-1908 (Box 15, Folder 5-8)
    The first of these three folders holds undated documents, which appear to date from circa 1902-1908. The second folder of the set holds various documents found together by the archivist dating from 1904-1908. The third folder begins the more ordered run of dated documents, starting principally with 1902 (there is one document each from 1900 and 1901).
  - Correspondence. Federation de l'Alliance (7 folders), 1905-1906 (Box 16, Folder 1-7)
    Among the many correspondents are Frank L. Warren, Jr., Felix Weill, J. LeRoy White, Camille Gorde, L. Fiedler, A. Bousquet, Maxime Ingres, Henry Cachard, W.H. Perkins, Rene Millet, Camille Thurwanger, Henry L. Rippe, F. C. de Sumichrast, Anatole Le Braz, A. Piatt Andrew, Julien Tiersot, Vicomte G. d'Avenel, Coudert Brothers.
  - Copypress letterbook., 1906-1907 January (Box 16, Folder 8)
    About 500 sheets of outgoing correspondence from Hyde and Gofflot. Correspondent index at back of volume.
  - Correspondence. Federation de l'Alliance (2 folders), 1907-1915 (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
  - Documents Divers. Federation de l'Alliance (2 folders), 1898-circa 1907 (Box 17, Folder 3-4)
    These two folders hold, among other documents, print matter related to the University of Grenoble's Committee of Patronage of Foreign Students, Alliance Francaise a Cincinnati, Bulletins, lists of lecturers, descriptions of the Alliance, and other documents concerning the Federation de l'Alliance Francaise aux Etats Unis et au Canada and the Cercle Francais de l'Universite Harvard (post-Hyde student years).
  - Correspondence. Federation l'Alliance (3 folders), 1921-1926 (Box 17, Folder 5-7)
  - Correspondence. Federation l'Alliance (7 folders), 1927-1935 (Box 18, Folder 1-7)
- Series IV. Diaries, 1922-1940; 12 Linear feet in 12 record cartons
  Hyde began maintaining a diary in early 1922, and he continued the practice until 1940 when the Nazis invaded France and he prepared to return to the United States after more than 30 years. Filling 94 loose leaf binders, the diaries' physical bulk consists of newspaper clippings and other print matter from American, French, British, and German publications glued to backing paper, sometimes with Hyde's brief, typed comments. A principal example are obituaries or other articles referring to a person's death; on these, Hyde typically recalled the extent of his relationship with the person, his impressions, and perhaps an anecdote. Threaded throughout the volumes are pages with Hyde's daily journal entries. These are typewritten, and references in the diaries (as well as occasional phonetic misspellings of English words) suggest that they were maintained by Hyde's secretaries at his dictation/direction rather than directly by his hand. The pages of each volume are numbered and many (perhaps all) volumes have an index to their content. The entries are in English, except that Hyde rendered quotations in French when, presumably, that is how he originally heard them, and in cases where Hyde used French to better express himself on a point. The clippings and other print matter are mostly English and French, but there are also a sizable number in German.
  Each daily entry extends to no more than two typed pages, and typically they are less than one full page. The general content of the entries is fairly consistent: an outline of Hyde's activities for the day with reference to the names of individuals he dined with, traveled with, attended a cultural event with, or otherwise encountered during the day, and to his physical condition. To these Hyde would commonly add a brief judgment, such as whether a person was pleasant or attractive, conversation interesting or not, the quality of a theatrical performance, museum exhibition, or other cultural event. The range of Hyde's social connections is impressive and includes American, French, British, and German diplomats, politicians, journalists and editors, industrialists and financiers, military officers, art historians and other academics, and individuals from the worlds of classical music and the theatre. Despite the richness of his connections, Hyde is inconsistent at documenting the substance of his many conversations. He documents various anecdotes, gossip, points of history, and other items of interest he hears but these seem lean compared to the settings and individuals involved. He seems most descriptive when discussing visits to museums, performances and other cultural matters. He seems the most reserved in conveying insight into himself, his business/financial matters, and his opinions on geopolitical events. It may be that the intermediation of secretaries, as well as his status as a foreigner living in France and his travels in countries such as Hitler's Germany and Mussolini's Italy, called for discretion in deciding what to dictate and have written down.
  Despite its shortcomings, the diaries do trace the experience of a wealthy, knowledgeable American expatriate in France from the years after World War I to the invasion of France early in World War II. Hyde's observations primarily concern geopolitics and culture, flavored with social gossip. Various observations, speculations, opinions about Germany and its relation to France and the rest of Europe are recorded here and there, and become more frequent and darker in the late 1930s, especially during the German annexations in 1938 of Austria and the Sudetenland. In this context, a notable thread that also appears increasingly over time in the diaries is Hyde's identification of individuals who are Jews; this is especially jarring as individuals Hyde often interacts with in the diaries (e.g., Hans Tietze) are suddenly referenced in that light.
  Hyde frequently attends the opera and theatre, and even movies, perhaps especially when traveling to Berlin, Vienna, and London. The diaries include many of the programs he collected at these performances. The stage actors Sacha Guitry and Yvonne Printemps appear frequently in Hyde's diary and there are some programs from their performances of Guitry's plays.
  In processing the diaries, the archivist skimmed Hyde's entries and attempted to identify any particular items of interest in the folder level scope notes below. The absence of any note at the folder level simply indicates that the above summary likely captures the general content of that volume. The folder level scope notes also outline when Hyde was traveling outside France; they do not necessarily document his travel within France or within a country he visited. The scope notes attempt to identify entries with some biographical significance concerning Hyde. These notes were developed within time constraints and so patrons should not rely exclusively on them.
  The diaries are in their original chronological order, by volume. For conservation reasons, the diary pages were removed from the original binders and placed in archival folders. The folders, as presented in the container list, retain the content structure of the original binders, most of which were discarded. A few of the original binders were retained as examples and these are noted in the container list.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of James Hazen Hyde, September 1948.
  - Diary, 1922 January-May (with original binder) (Box 19, Folder 1)
    Among others, records meetings with Ambassador Herrick, Count Bertrand d'Aramond, Norwegian minister de Wedel-Jarlsberg, General Mangin, Andre Tardieu, Marshal Foch, Hughes Le Roux, former Ambassador Wallace, French minister Sarraut, financier Andre Benac (who tells an anecdote concerning Benac's view of what sparked the start of World War I), embassy counsellor Sheldon Whitehouse, Adolph Ochs. Travels to Spain in April-May, and records in detail conversations, art, impressions while traveling largely with the Bynes.
  - Diary, 1922 June-December (2 folders) (Box 19, Folder 2-3)
    Summarizes his meeting with Georges Clemenceau (October 14), primarily concerning advice on Clemenceau's upcoming trip to the U.S.
  - Diary, 1923 January-March (2 folders) (Box 19, Folder 4-5)
    In reaction to the death of Sarah Bernhardt, Hyde recalls her performances and his occasional meetings with her. Includes a letter from Associated Press journalist Joseph E. Sharkey with his typed article as submitted about Andre Tardieu, acknowledging that it was the outcome of a dinner with Hyde.
  - Diary, 1923 April-July (2 folders) (Box 19, Folder 6-7)
    Includes summaries of discussions with Mortimer Schiff (of Kuhn, Loeb) and Ivy Lee about the economic situation in Europe, specifically an Austrian loan (Lee returns to the loan in detail in the diary for March 22, 1924). Includes a page of Vogue magazine that has a photo of Mrs. James Hazen Hyde and her son (page 136 of the diary).
  - Diary, 1923 August-October (2 folders) (Box 19, Folder 8-9)
    Appointed Grand Officer of French Legion d'Honneur.
  - Diary, 1923 November-December (2 folders) (Box 19, Folder 10-11)
  - Diary, 1924 January-February (2 folders) (Box 19, Folder 12-13)
  - Diary, 1924 March-April (2 folders) (Box 19, Folder 14-15)
    Recounted a story regarding antique furniture owned by a friend, which was taken by Germany and subsequently returned to its owners multiple times.
  - Diary, 1924 May-June (with original binder) (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1924 June-September (2 folders) (Box 20, Folder 2-3)
  - Diary, 1924 October-December (2 folders) (Box 20, Folder 4-5)
    Traveled to Egypt and along the Nile wth Cook's Service, beginning in November. Visits the camp of Professor Reisner of Harvard with Madame Foucard, as well as several other ancient sites. Comments on the restrictions placed on foreign archeologists by the Egyptian government. Also visits the president of American University and others, and makes observations about the culture, architecture, military, politics, etc. The account of the trip continues in the next two diaries.
  - Diary, 1925 January-February (Box 20, Folder 6)
    Account of Hyde's visit to Egypt continues for this entire diary. On February 3, he meets with Professor Breasted who explains his process for photographing and documenting the hieroglyphics found (he meets with Breasted on later dates in the diary as well). Includes typescripts of letters from Ronald Storrs writing from Jerusalem seeking support for a cultural center that would unite peoples across the region's religions. On February 10, Hyde describes his meeting with King Fouad I.
  - Diary, 1925 March-April (Box 20, Folder 7)
    Hyde's Egyptian trip ends in early March. He goes to Italy, where he briefly meets the Pope in Rome (March 25); he returns to Versailles by early April.
  - Diary, 1925 May-July (Box 20, Folder 8)
    Page 47 of the diary is a supplement to the European edition of the New York Herald that includes some photos of Hyde's Paris residence.
  - Diary, 1925 August-October (Box 20, Folder 9)
    Attended the exhibition of Decorative Arts at least three times and is impressed with its beauty and influence.
  - Diary, 1925 November-December (with original binder) (Box 20, Folder 10)
    Traveled to Geneva, visited the League of Nations. Commented that Switzerland itself was a difficult country to govern due to it being home to a multitude of cultures and languages. Traveled on to Italy, specifically Milan and Rome. Begins to think that Germany can remain stable, however the disposition of Mussolini in Italy would lead to civil war.
  - Diary, "Supplement Coupures," October 1924-April 1926, 1924-1926 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    Contains only newspaper clippings (in French) with little commentary and no diary entries.
  - Diary, 1926 January-March (Box 21, Folder 2)
    Attended a meeting for the committee of the statue commemorating the battle of the Marne, which included the sculptor MacMonnies. Ambassador Herrick also attended, and Hyde recounts favorable anecdotes Herrick told about Aristide Briand. Includes a letter from Franz Boas requesting financial support for the Emergency Society for German and Austrian Science and Art.
  - Diary, 1926 April-June (2 folders) (Box 21, Folder 3-4)
    Travels to London for an extended stay. Has dinner with the American ambassador, Lady Astor, and many others. Visits theatres, museums, private collections, and shops for artworks. His diary about the trip extends briefly into July, in the next volume.
  - Diary, 1926 July-November (2 folders) (Box 21, Folder 5-6)
    See also the following diary, which includes out-of-sequence pages for early July when Hyde was in London.
  - Diary, 1926 July, November-December; 1927 January, 1926-1927 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    This diary holds the early weeks of July 1926, when Hyde was still in London, then jumps to November 1926. The gap months are in the previous volume. Travels to Genoa from late November to mid-December; this trip appears to be centered primarily on cultural visits. Afterward he goes to Rome, where his visit is the usual mix of politics, geopolitics, economics, culture, etc.; describes at length a pontifical mass he attended (December 31, 1926). On December 26, he dines with Countess Matuschka, who appears several times in later entries; she is likely the Countess he marries in 1930.
  - Diary, 1927 February-May (2 folders) (Box 21, Folder 8-9)
    Account of trip to Rome continues to March; has glimpse of Mussolini on horseback and has a favorable impression.
  - Diary, "Voyage Londres" 1927 May-July (Box 21, Folder 10)
    Travels to London in mid-May and is there throughout this diary.
  - Diary, 1927 August-December (with original binder) (Box 21, Folder 11)
    London trip ends at start of diary, on August 2.
  - Diary, 1928 January-March (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1928 March-May (Box 22, Folder 2)
    Traveled to Berlin with side trips to Potsdam, begining April 12. Saw a "speaking cinema," went to the theatre, visited cultural sites and museums, shopped for artwork. Among others saw Friedlander, Kahn, Breasted, Wiegand. Makes reference to Berlin being a "paradise" for Jews (page 358 of the diary).
  - Diary, 1928 June-August (Box 22, Folder 3)
    Account of his trip to Berlin continues; leaves Berlin on June 25, stopping in Baden-Baden before arriving back at Versailles on July 16.
  - Diary, 1928 September-November (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Diary, 1928 November-1929 January, 1928-1929 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    Includes many clippings (one with a photograph) concerning Hyde's receipt of the Grand Croix of the Legion of Honor.
  - Diary, 1929 January-February (with original binder) (Box 22, Folder 6)
    Looked at past philosophical works, including Voltaire. Did not enjoy their works as a form of poetry, but understood this was contemporary writing for the 18th century.
  - Diary, 1929 March-April (Box 22, Folder 7)
    Travels to the Riviera for March and into mid-April. Extensive clippings on the death of Ambassador Myron Herrick, a major presence in Hyde's diaries.
  - Diary, 1929 May-July (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Diary, 1929 July-October (Box 22, Folder 9)
    On September 28, Hyde spends the day with Countess Matuschka, who tells him of some of her experiences during the years of World War I. She appears in several entries around this time. The diary includes a copy of the program for Guitry's "Histoires de France" performed at the Theatre Pigalle.
  - Diary, 1929 November-December (1 of 2 folders) (Box 22, Folder 10)
    In November, visits Wiesbaden, Mainz, Frankfurt, Cologne, and elsewhere in Germany (at least in part with Herbert Haseltine and Raymond Recouly); makes several observations about German-French relations in the Rhineland and military matters, as well as cultural visits. On the occasion of Clemenceau's death, Hyde records various personal and second hand recollections of the former prime minister.
  - Diary, 1929 November-December (1 of 2 folders) (Box 23, Folder 1)
    Substantive summary of Hyde's meeting with Minister of the Interior André Tardieu (December 5), principally concerning French-German relations, and Hyde's first meeting with and advice to the new US Ambassador, Walter Edge (December 18). In reaction to a newspaper piece recalling Henry Frick's death in 1919, Hyde expresses bitterness about Frick in relation to the "Equitable row."
  - Diary, 1930 January-March (with original binder) (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Diary, 1930 April-June (Box 23, Folder 3)
    Hyde travels to Germany, including Frankfurt, Dresden, Nuremberg, and Munich, beginning on April 14 and continuing through the entire volume. Initially meets with French General Guillaumat who believes there will be another war with Germany, which is building a military superior to that of France. Most of the entries concern visits to private collections, museums, and residences.
  - Diary, 1930 July-September (2 folders) (Box 23, Folder 4-5)
    Hyde's travels in Germany continue, in Munich, ending late July; he visits collections there with Countess Matuschka.
  - Diary, 1930 October-November (Box 23, Folder 6)
    In October, the Countess Matuschka visits Hyde in Versailles, seeing his house for the first time; on October 28, a passing reference to his engagement to her. A couple of related clippings (with pictures) at page 101-102.
  - Diary, 1930 December (Box 23, Folder 7)
    Includes Hyde's entry of December 8, the day of his wedding to Ella Matuschka; includes clippings, some with photos of the couple at the wedding, with Andre Tardieu.
  - Diary, 1931 January-February (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Diary, 1931 March-May (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Diary, 1931 June-August (2 folders) (Box 24, Folder 1-2)
    On June 15, Hyde travels to begin a trip to London, returning to France in early July. On June 16, notes his decision to write a letter of separation from his wife, Ella, who is in Italy.
  - Diary, 1931 September-October (Box 24, Folder 3)
    Travels to Berlin and Potsdam beginning September 30, with Raymond Recouly for much of the trip, ending on October 21. Some individuals he visits voice negative views on the situation in Germany, referring to the Nazis, anti-Semitism, and the financial conditions. He saw a shop in Berlin where silk stockings were mounted on a wax nude figurine, rather than on legs only, and he found this indecent. He describes at length a play by Karl Heinz Martin he sees in the communist quarter of Berlin and comes away impressed.
  - Diary, 1931 November-December (Box 24, Folder 4)
    On December 1, meets the King of Spain at the Chateau de Champs with Dr. Hensler, Cahen d'Anvers, and others.
  - Diary, 1932 January-February (Box 24, Folder 5)
    Includes a panoramic night photo of Harvard across the water (page 49). Includes a photo of Hyde at the Institut d'Aix en Provence, February 18 (page 170).
  - Diary, 1932 June-August (Box 24, Folder 6)
    There is no diary in the collection for March-May 1932. This diary begins in June with Hyde traveling in Germany, until late June. Citizen's arriving late to an opera led to the belief that Germany had lost its sense of discipline since the Reich's takeover.
  - Diary, 1932 September-October (Box 24, Folder 7)
    Includes clippings, program, ephemera, and entries concerning the dedication of Frederick MacMonnies's Marne monument (early-mid September). Hyde is married for a third time, on October 8, to Mme. Thome (commonly referred to as "T" or "Tommie" in the entries). On October 17, they travel to London.
  - Diary, 1932 November-December (Box 24, Folder 8)
    Includes a "listes conferences et articles" from 1913-1918 by Hyde. Hyde's and his wife's visit in London continues, returning to France in early December.
  - Diary, 1933 January (with original binder) (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Diary, 1933 February (Box 25, Folder 1)
    On February 7, Hyde learns of the suicide of Henry Rippe, his "confidential secretary and friend" and "last link with my American business friends."
  - Diary, 1933 March (Box 25, Folder 2)